so hi my name is Joe brewer and I'm a
change strategist and today I want to do
a book review on this amazing book right
here butterfly economics by Paul Ormerod
the subtitle is a new general theory of
social and economic behavior and this
book would fit into the category of what
I would call complexity economics
meaning that Paul is taking a
perspective informed by complexity
science to explain how economic systems
work and what's really excellent about
this book is he flips traditional
economic theory on its head now
traditional economic theory I'm really
referring to what's called neoclassical
economics which looks at economic
systems as complete Gestalt so there is
an economy as a monolithic thing and you
look at its behavior as a monolithic
thing and you have assumptions about how
it works and for those of you have
studied the history of economic
scholarship you'll know that all of the
major assumptions of neoclassical
economics have been falsified they are
don't hold up to the scrutiny of
observational experience and so the
question that Paul is asking is what if
we were to instead look at economics
from the bottom up and rather than
looking at it as a monolithic uniform
thing look at it as a collection of
small interacting agents that have some
relationship to each other and see how
those interactions between a large
number of small entities can create the
emergent macro scale behavior that we
see in economic systems and so he does
this by starting with some fascinating
research that's been done with ant
colonies where they would take a colony
of ants and give them to food supplies
that are equally distant from each other
so if you were to imagine that right
here is where the colony is and then you
were to go from it to two locations
where there's a pile of sugar say and
you watch as ants go out to one of the
food supplies and leave their little
Chemical trails to tell the other ants
whether or not they
food you'll see this fascinating
emergent dynamic that at some point in
time there will be a majority like
eighty percent of the ants will have
gone over to the pile that's over here
but then at another time rather abruptly
eighty percent will switched and gone
over to the pile that's over here and
there's this chaotic back and forth they
never stabilize into one pile or the
other and if you were to take the
average across the large amount of time
you find that the ants spend about half
their time at each of the piles but
that's not really a useful measure for
the amazing complexity and details
granular instability and chaos the
turbulence latest scene in the actual
behavior dance if you take the same way
of thinking and apply it to economic
systems and look at say the way that
different firms behave in an economy
where there are some firms that are
small and they're rapidly growing
disrupting with new technologies that
are causing other firms to go extinct or
to go bankrupt and close their doors
where there are firms that are
interacting with each other to merge and
form conglomerates or to be divided and
broken off and sold as pieces that
they're all these interacting patterns
that arise the behaviors between the
different firms and when you look at all
of those interacting behaviors together
you're able to see an emergent pattern
of behavior which is the overall
behavior of the economic system so
taking this way of thinking of looking
at economies as a bunch of interacting
agents who have some rules that
determine what their likely strategies
are and how they interact with each
other that you can run modeling and
simulation studies using a computer to
see the behaviors that pop out and he
have some fascinating examples from
economic policy that look at social
issues and one that I found especially
compelling was a discussion he had about
policies that are intended to increase
public safety by reducing crime on the
streets and what he showed was that in
certain economic conditions where you
have a measure of seiya a ten percent
rate of some kind of crime like
the people breaking into houses that if
you introduce a certain policy into that
environment it will reduce the amount of
crime but in another situation that has
a different set of background conditions
where the crime rate is exactly the same
meaning that ten percent of the houses
are being broken into in a given period
of time that if you introduce the same
policy crime rates will go up now what's
going on where the same policy leads to
opposite outcomes it turns out that
these interacting localized behaviors in
this case the way that the policy
influences the behavior of people in the
market in the economic system that in
certain contexts it will reduce crime in
other contexts it will incentivize and
directly other forms of activity that
lead to increases in crime and so the
thing that we can take away from this is
that anyone who claims that in economic
policy is going to only have one
behavioural outcome for economies if
someone you might want to be at least
skeptical of and look more closely at
the way that the patterns of human
interaction lead to the macro scale
statistical behavior of that system and
that this complexity approach that looks
at the interacting parts to see how the
macro behavior emerges will tell you
whether a policy is appropriate to a
given context or not now clearly this is
a very different way of thinking about
economic policy and economic planning a
very different way of thinking about how
to interpret statistics where
specifically you do not treat statistics
as standalone measurements but instead
you contextualise them to the emerging
patterns of behavior in the system when
you're making the measurement and if you
have an understanding of what the
behaviors are at the smaller scale that
are leading to that emergent pattern
then you'll have some predictive ability
about what that metric means but if you
don't have an understanding of how the
metric maps to these more granular
dynamic interactions and the evolving
pattern of the social system then you
may interpret the measurement
incorrectly and introduce a policy tool
that is inappropriate to the situation
at hand
so thinking in this way is very
different from how economic policy has
been done in the past it's a great
example of how complexity science can
transform how we think about economic
policy and economic theory and so I
really encourage you to get your own
copy of this book butterfly economics
and learn more enjoy